A Guide to the Papers of George Washington, 1752-1999
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of George Washington, 1752-1999
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Multiple numbers
ca. 48 items
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This collection was acquired through gift and purchase, ca. 1930-present.
Biographical/Historical Information
First President of the United States, 1789-1797
Born: February 22, 1732 in Westmoreland County, Virginia
Died: December 14, 1799 in Mount Vernon, Virginia
Married to Martha Dandridge Washington
On April 30, 1789, George Washington, standing on the balcony of Federal Hall on Wall Street in New York, took his oath of office as the first President of the United States. "As the first of every thing, in our situation will serve to establish a Precedent," he wrote James Madison, "it is devoutly wished on my part, that these precedents may be fixed on true principles."
Born in 1732 into a Virginia planter family, he learned the morals, manners, and body of knowledge requisite for an 18th century Virginia gentleman.
He pursued two intertwined interests: military arts and western expansion. At 16 he helped survey Shenandoah lands for Thomas, Lord Fairfax. Commissioned a lieutenant colonel in 1754, he fought the first skirmishes of what grew into the French and Indian War. The next year, as an aide to Gen. Edward Braddock, he escaped injury although four bullets ripped his coat and two horses were shot from under him.
From 1759 to the outbreak of the American Revolution, Washington managed his lands around Mount Vernon and served in the Virginia House of Burgesses. Married to a widow, Martha Dandridge Custis, he devoted himself to a busy and happy life. But like his fellow planters, Washington felt himself exploited by British merchants and hampered by British regulations. As the quarrel with the mother country grew acute, he moderately but firmly voiced his resistance to the restrictions.
When the Second Continental Congress assembled in Philadelphia in May 1775, Washington, one of the Virginia delegates, was elected Commander in Chief of the Continental Army. On July 3, 1775, at Cambridge, Massachusetts, he took command of his ill-trained troops and embarked upon a war that was to last six grueling years.
He realized early that the best strategy was to harass the British. He reported to Congress, "we should on all Occasions avoid a general Action, or put anything to the Risque, unless compelled by a necessity, into which we ought never to be drawn." Ensuing battles saw him fall back slowly, then strike unexpectedly. Finally in 1781 with the aid of French allies--he forced the surrender of Cornwallis at Yorktown.
Washington longed to retire to his fields at Mount Vernon. But he soon realized that the Nation under its Articles of Confederation was not functioning well, so he became a prime mover in the steps leading to the Constitutional Convention at Philadelphia in 1787. When the new Constitution was ratified, the Electoral College unanimously elected Washington President
He did not infringe upon the policy making powers that he felt the Constitution gave Congress. But the determination of foreign policy became preponderantly a Presidential concern. When the French Revolution led to a major war between France and England, Washington refused to accept entirely the recommendations of either his Secretary of State Thomas Jefferson, who was pro-French, or his Secretary of the Treasury Alexander Hamilton, who was pro-British. Rather, he insisted upon a neutral course until the United States could grow stronger.
To his disappointment, two parties were developing by the end of his first term. Wearied of politics, feeling old, he retired at the end of his second. In his Farewell Address, he urged his countrymen to forswear excessive party spirit and geographical distinctions. In foreign affairs, he warned against long-term alliances.
Washington enjoyed less than three years of retirement at Mount Vernon, for he died of a throat infection December 14, 1799. For months the Nation mourned him.
Scope and Content
This collection consists of ca. 42 items, chiefly letters to and from George Washington.
Contents List
- George Washington to William Fauntleroy 1752 May 20, ALS, 1 p.
  #6693-c. Washington requests permission to "wait on Miss Betsy in hopes of a revocation of the former cruel sentence ...."
- George Washington to Governor Robert Dinwiddie 1754 March 20, ALS, 3 p., photostat.
  #7289-b. Washington thanks Dinwiddie for his commission as Lieutenant Colonel, and advises him of the current situation of the Virginia troops and their lack of officers, his plan to promote Lt. Van Braam, and the ordering of troops to Winchester prior to Washington's 2nd Expedition to the Ohio.
- George Washington to Governor Robert Dinwiddie 1755 July 18, ALS, 1 p.
  Barrow, #2027. Washington describes Braddock's defeat on the Monongehala River on July 9th, declaring "Our poor Virginians behaved like men and dyed like Soldiers for I believe out of three Companys that were there that day Scarce 30 was left alive...." He fears the defeat will force the abandonment of the back country by the settlers unless means are taken to insure their protection. A postscript lists Virginia officers killed and wounded.
- John Baylor to George Washington 1756 June 7, ALS, 1 p.
  #5951. Baylor thanks Washington for his kindness when Baylor was with the militia in Winchester, and promises he will have deserters caught and sent back. He sends his compliments to the other officers.
- Andrew Lewis to George Washington 1770 March 1, ALS, 2 p.
  #3620. Lewis writes concerning land claims of soldiers who had served under Washington in 1756.
- Bookplate [1771], D, 1 p.; copperplate engraving.
  #13483. An adaptation of the Washington family coat of arms. Washington ordered the original copper engraving and 300 prints of his bookplate from London in 1771. The bookplate also contains the family motto, "Exitus Acta Probat," which translates as "The end proves [or justifies] the deed."
- George Washington to James Wood 1774 February 20, ALS, 1 p.; negative photocopy; location of original unknown.
  #4562. Washington writes regarding Wood's survey of lands along the Mississippi River.
- George Washington to Jonathan Trumbull 1775 October 5, LS, 1 p.
  #10576. Washington sends Governor Trumbull the latest military news, particularly the sailing of a small British fleet from Boston which he fears may bombard a coastal town. He mentions the recall of General Gage and his replacement by General Howe, and notes that Gage's account of Bunker Hill tallies with his own in regard to number of casualties.
- George Washington to Burwell Bassett 1775 June 22, D, 1 p.; typed transcription; location of original unknown.
  #38-532. Washington writes regarding his appointment to command the Continental Army, Congress' approval of a Continental currency, and inviting Bassett to visit his wife at Mount Vernon.
- George Washington to Martha Washington 1775 June 23, ALS, 1 p.; photocopy; location of original unknown.
  #38-532. Washington writes regarding his departure from Philadelphia and his affection for her.
- George Washington to General William Heath 1776 September 5, ALS, 2 p.
  #9671. Washington instructs General Heath to obtain intelligence necessary for the defense of New York, and to harass enemy troops if feasible.
- George Washington to Robert Morris 1777 March 2, ALS, 6 p.
  #9375. Washington assesses the strengths and weaknesses of General Howe's forces and the probability he will attack Philadelphia, and expresses dismay at the treatment of Hessian prisoners of war. After analyzing the current situation of his army and the British army he notes "It is with difficulty (if I may use the expression) that I can keep the life and soul of this Army together."
- George Washington to Colonel Landon Carter 1777 April 15, ALS, 2 p.
  #9791. Washington writes about the condition of the Continental Army after the winter and speculates on the British Army's next move. He comments on his desire for a speedy conclusion to the war and subsequent retirement.
- George Washington to Col. Elias Dayton 1777 August 6, ALS, 1 p., with attached address leaf; docketed; silked.
  #13481. Given in honor of Hope McCurdy Olmsted. Washington writes to Dayton from his Camp at Germantown, 1777 August 6, enclosing an undelivered letter sent previously (not present). Dayton is orderd to halt due to uncertainty as to the destination of the British fleet and then to "march to Peekskill upon receiving authentic intelligence that the Fleet have again arrived at the Hook or any where upon the Coast of New England."
- George Washington to James Potter 1777 November 17, NS, 1 p.; docketed.
  #15686. Washington acknowledges the receipt of Potter's letter in which "Col. Greene's letter" was enclosed [neither present]. Washington has "had the account of Fort Mifflin being evacuated." He tells Potter that the "fascines which you were to make may still be wanted, tho' the Army is not to cross the Schuylkill for some time." Washington tells Potter not to collect the brushwood for the fascines "all at any one place, or they might become an object of the enemy's attention & occasion an attempt to destroy them." The letter is in an unidentified secretarial hand and signed by Washington.
- George Washington to James Wood 1778 September 19, ALS, 1 p.; negative photocopy; location of original unknown.
  #4562. Washington writes concerning reenlisting the services of the Virginia troops under Wood's command.
- George Washington to Theodorick Bland 1779 February 28, L, 2 p.; contemporary copy.
  Washington orders Bland to oversee the convention barracks of Hessian prisoners at Charlottesville, Va. On the reverse is copy of a resolution from General Bond for Charles Thompson in Congress, August 21, 1779, concerning quarters for Hessian soldiers in Virginia. #9803
- Page from an account book mentioning George Washington 1780 April, D, 1 p., partially printed.
  #8136-a. An entry mentions the purchase of a periwig for "Genl. Washington's entertainment."
- Edmund Randolph to George Washington 1782 January 8, ALS, 1 p.
  #11632. Randolph conveys to Washington "the vote of the Virginia assembly, expressing their sentiments of your conduct and exertions at York," declares his own sentiments in accord and asks Washington to forward an enclosure to Lafayette.
- George Washington to Joshua Barney 1784 March 29, ALS, 4 p.; photocopy. Original privately owned.
  #8265-c. Washington thanks Captain Barney for his care of packages sent by the Marquis de Lafayette which he asks Barney to store with Thomas Jefferson in Annapolis. He will send a carriage for them and pay expenses.
- Invitation [1784], D, 1 p.; in unidentified hand.
  #3490-a. Mr. and Mrs. Washington invite Mr. and Mrs. Nourse to dinner at Fairfield on Friday.
- James Rumsey to William Hartshorne 1785 October 24 and 27, ALS, 4 p.; Barrow.
  #6044. Rumsey writes concerning payment of workers of the Potomac Company; signed by George Washington and others.
- George Washington to Humphrey 1786 June 20, ALS, 1 p. photostat and photographic negatives. Original at Mount Vernon.
- Society of the Cincinnati membership certificate 1787 March 1, D., 1 p.; photocopy.
  #9251. Certificate of membership for Daniel Bedinger; signed by George Washington. Location of original unknown.
- George Washington to David Stuart 1787 November 5, ALS, 2 p.
  #8122. Washington writes concerning the adoption of the U.S. Constitution, mentioning Charles Lee, Samuel Chase, the payment of British debts, and the purchase of corn.
- George Washington to David Stuart 1788 January 18, ALS, 1 p.
  #8122. Washington inquires about a slave he has hired from Mrs. Stuart whose term of service was up at Christmas.
- George Washington answer to a bill of complaint by W. Owens 1789 February 15, ADS, 2 p.
  #382-d. Washington responds to a bill of complaint filed in Fairfax County, Va., by William Owens, in a case concerning the estate of George Mercer.
- George Washington to Gov. [John] Hancock 1789 May 9, ALS, 1 p.; docketed; Barrow.
  #10530-c. Washington replies to a letter from Hancock congratulating him on his election to the presidency.
- George Washington to David Stuart 1789 September 21, NS, 1 p.
  #8122. Washington's brief note covers an enclosure [not present] regarding a compromise with "Alexander."
- George Washington to David Stuart 1790 June 15, AL, 4 p.
  #8122. An incomplete letter concerns the irritation of the public with the proceedings and practices of Congress and the assumption of state Revolutionary War debts.
- Address panel 1790, AD, 1 p.
  #11017. Addressed in Washington's hand to Mr. Robert Lewis, near Fauquier Court House, Virginia.
- Oliver Towles to George Washington 1791 February 20, ALS, 2 p.
  #2447. Towles asks Washington to verify the particulars of an incident in which Washington, as Commander in Chief, did not allow Towles to resign his commission in the army at the time of "so perilous a crisis" in 1777.
- Richard M. Greaton Commission 1793 March 19, D, 1 p.
  #8041. Signed by George Washington and Henry Knox, Richard M. Greaton commissioned at the rank of Captain in the second sublegion of the United States.
- George Washington to James Madison 1793 October 14, ALS, 4 p. on 1 l.; docketed; silked.
  #13481. Given in honor of Hope McCurdy Olmsted. In a letter marked "Private," Washington writes to Madison from Mount Vernon, 1793 October 14, concerning "the calamitous situation of Philadelphia," i.e. the Yellow Fever epidemic. He seeks Madison's advice on the legality of the Executive convening Congress at Germantown, or some other place. He mentions that he has requested an official opinion from the Attorney-General and has also sought Thomas Jefferson's advice. He notes that Governor Thomas Mifflin has reported 3500 deaths and that Philadelphia is "now almost depopulated by removals and death."
- George Washington to Joseph Barrell 1794 March 30, ALS, 1 p.
  #9030. Washington thanks Barrell for a gift of a sea otter skin.
- Cary Seldon [sic] to George Washington 1794 July 20, 2 pp. on 1 leaf, with detached address leaf; Barrow process; much loss of text on left margin
  #38-301. Bill and receipt, written and signed by overseer William Pearce, to Selden for horse breeding services at Mount Vernon. On verso of address leaf is a letter signed "Chas. W. Farrand," a Union soldier, written from the vicinity of Fredericksburg, Va. probably in the spring of 1862.
- George Washington to Henry Tazewell 1795 March 3, LS, 1 p.
  #10036. A form letter signed by Washington directs Henry Tazewell as U.S. Senators from Virginia to come to a session in Philadelphia to deliberate on "matters touching the public good."
- George Washington to George Lewis 1795 September 28, ALS, 2 p.
  #3086-a. Washington writes regarding a possible visit by Lewis and a land sale involving Henry Lee and Alexander Spotswood. (Harriot?)
- George Washington to Tristram Thomas 1795 September 14, ALS, 2 p. on 1 l., with attached address leaf; free franked by Washington.
  #15686. Washingto replies to "the address and resolutions of the Citizens of Cheraw District, who assembled on the 15th of August, to express their opinions on the treaty, and who desired my sanction might be withheld." Washington states that it is now widely known that the treaty "has received my assent" and regrets that "this should differ from that of any of my fellow citizens, but I have conscientiously done what appeared to be my duty." He thanks the citizens of Cheraw for the "respectful and grateful sentiments of the meeting, flowing, as they are pleased to say from a recollection of my former services." Washington concludes by stating that he wishes to assure them that if his "sincere endeavours to promote the interest of my fellow citizens, ever entitled me to their approbation, I have not by this act ceased to deserve it."
- "Extract from Gen. Washington's Speech to Both Houses of Congress" 1796 December 7, AMs, 1 p.
  #5025. Washington proposes the establishment of a national university and a military academy. A tally of ayes and noes is on verso together with other notes concerning the proposal, including one regarding a similar proposal by Jefferson.
- George Washington to General [William] Heath 1797 May 20, ALS, 1 p.; split at fold lines. Bequest of Paul Mellon.
  #11629. Washington assures Heath that he did not attribute any motive of office seeking to a congratulatory letter Heath wrote; hopes that the country will avoid the current European crisis and "do justice to all, and have no political connexion with any of the European powers" and looks forward to reading Heath's memoirs. He writes in closing that "my hours...glide smoothly on," and "the prosperity of our country will always have the first place in my thoughts" while farming will occupy his remaining days.
- George Washington to Colonel Edward Carrington 1797 June 26, ALS, 1 p.
  #2529. Washington writes concerning Mr. Booker's improved threshing machine which he wishes to try.
- George Washington to John Langhorne 1797 October 15, ALS, 2 p.; Tracy W. McGregor Library.
  #1231. Washington deplores public attacks upon the government but declares he is impervious to attacks upon him personally as his is now in his long sought retirement.
- William Heth to George Washington 1798 July 30, ALS, 2 p.
  #38-114. Heth writes regarding "enemies to our government" and the dangers of partisan politics, and the necessity of counteracting with a pamphlet he has written "for the perusal of the plain farmers."
- George Washington, Mount Vernon, to Landon Carter 1798 October 5, Photocopy and typescript. Location of originals unknown.
  Regarding Washington's health in his declining years. Enclosed is a letter to John McDowell, President of St. John's College, introducing Carter, who was enrolling his sons at the college. #1445
- George Washington, Mount Vernon, to Cashier of the Office of the Discount & Deposit, Baltimore 1798 December 6, Negative photocopy. Location of originals unknown.
  #1445 Washington authorizes payment of $283.00 to Edward Livingston.
- George Washington to General Marshall and Colonels Carrington and Heth 1799 May 12, ALS, 2 p.; in unidentified hand.
  #38-114. Washington has been so long away from his home county that he does not feel competent to suggest men to be selected as militia officers. He leaves the task to the three recipients. He supports the creation of a militia against a future emergency and encloses a division and subdivision of the state into recruiting and rendezvousing districts and a list of officer quotas for the 12 Virginia regiments.
- Diary of Tobias Lear 1803 June 24-October 23, 1 vol.
  Lear discusses his day-to-day affairs including marriage to "my dear Fanny" [Frances Dandridge Henley]; boarding with [Thomas?] Law; initiation in the Masonic Lodge at Alexandria; dining with Jefferson and Madison, news of the Louisiana Purchase; July 4th celebration; journey to Boston via Baltimore, Philadelphia, and New York; visit to his Portsmouth, N.H. home; a rumor, begun by John Marshall, that he had suppressed certain papers of George Washington; and preparations for the journey to Algiers on the U.S.S. Constitution under Edward P reble [no entries the month of the voyage.]
  Lear writes at length about his diplomatic mission to Algiers to negotiate a treaty with Tripoli and the current situation with the Barbary pirates. He discusses the capture of an American brig; the replacement of Commodore Richard Morris; assistance to the H.M.S. Childers,an English brig in distress, whose captain, Sir George Bolton, was carrying dispatches to Lord Nelson; discussions on Barbary affairs with consuls James L. Cathcart and James Simpson; the arrival of the Emperor of Morocco in Tangiers and subsequent negotiations including ratification of the Treay of 1786; and attempts by British men of war to lure away American sailors. The diary ends on October 23, a week before the capture of William Bainbridge and the crew of the Philadelphia.
  #13752.
- George Washington to David Stuart [n.y.] December 13, Address leaf.
  #8122.
- George Washington to Benjamin Harrison n.d., 2 pp. on 1 l.; 19th century copy in unidentified hand.
  Washington states that "ammunition, tho' competent to the defensive, is, by a late estimate of the commanding officer of artillery, vastly short of an offensive operation of any consequence." He says that the army does not have enough clothing for "the few recruits which may be expected" and unless the supply from France arrives "the troops must, next winter, go naked, unless their states supply them." Washington says that the "proportion of the Continental Army already allotted to Southern service is as much as ... can be spared for that purpose." He says that he will do all in his power to "give support to the Southern States, but you may readily conceive how irksome a thing it must be to me to be called upon for assistance, when I have not the means of affording it."
  #5605.
- Map of Washington's Mount Vernon Estate 1951, D, 1 p.; photostat and photographic negatives.
  Published 1951 by the Washington Library, San Mateo, Calif.
- "Copies of Three Original Letters from General Washington, Now (1893) in the Possession of Rev. Dr. Brand" 1999 August 20, D, 4 p.; typed transcriptions by David C. Hodge.
  1797 May 29, George Washington to James McHenry. Washington describes his daily round of activities which prevent him from responding to correspondence quickly.
  1798 May 6, George Washington to James McHenry. Washington inquires about the establishment of an arsenal at the mouth of the Shenandoah which he believes the best situated place in the entire United States, and comments briefly on the disarray in Democratic party following the publication of dispatches from U. S. envoys abroad.
  1798 December 16, George Washington to James McHenry. Washington advises McHenry on the proper way to set up a military system, with a few principal officers who would communicate with the War Dept. He accepted command of the army, but will not be active unless his presence is required in the field. Direction of military affairs in the southern states should go to General Pinckney. General Hamilton should superintend all troops and posts not under Pinckney including the army under Wilkinson. The recruiting service should be under the Inspector General. "This will serve to unite and simplify...and enable you to devote your attention to ... general Plans and to an effectual Superintencence...."
  #11550